## Baris Kasikci

 $Assistant\ Professor$  Electrical Engineering and Computer Science University of Michigan

4820 BBB 2260 Hayward Street Ann Arbor, MI 48109, USA  $+1 \ (734) \ 763\text{-}1560$ barisk@umich.edu

http://web.eecs.umich.edu/~barisk

### RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research is centered around developing techniques, tools, and environments that help us build more reliable, secure, and efficient systems. I am interested in developing techniques and building systems that allow programmers to better reason about their code. I am also interested in system support for emerging hardware platforms, efficient runtime instrumentation, hardware and runtime support for enhancing system security, program analysis, and formal verification.

### **EDUCATION**

## Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL)

Lausanne, Switzerland

PhD in Computer Science Sep. 2010–Dec. 2015

Thesis: Techniques for Detection, Root Cause Diagnosis,

and Classification of In-Production Concurrency Bugs

Advisor: Prof. George Candea

### Middle East Technical University (METU)

Ankara, Turkey

M.Sc. in Electrical and Electronics Engineering Sep. 2006–Jun. 2009

Thesis: Variability Modeling in Software Product Lines

Graduated with the top grade Advisor: Prof. Semih Bilgen

B.Sc. in Electrical and Electronics Engineering

Project: Embedded Target Estimation, Detection, and Tracking

Graduated with High Honors Advisor: Prof. Arzu Koc

Sep. 2002–Jun. 2006

### AWARDS AND HONORS NSF CAREER Award 2020 2020 Intel Rising Star Award IEEE Micro Top Pick Honorable Mention, "NDA" 2020 Google Faculty Research Award 2019 IEEE Micro Top Pick, "Foreshadow" 2019 Intel Faculty Award 2019 Jay Lepreau Best Paper Award, OSDI 2018 Intel Faculty Award 2018 Outstanding Reviewer Award, WWW 2017 Patrick Denantes Memorial Prize for outstanding PhD thesis, EPFL 2016 EuroSys Roger Needham Award for Best PhD. Thesis in Computer Systems in Europe 2016 Intel Corp. Software and Services Group, Grant 2014 - 2016VMware Inc., Doctoral Fellowship 2014-2015 EPFL, Doctoral Fellowship 2010-2011 Scientific and Technological Research Council of Turkey, Master Scholarship 2006-2008 Funding NSF CAREER grant, 576K USD, PI 2020 NSF/Intel FoMR grant, 180K USD (360K USD total), co-PI 2020 NSF FMitF grant, 375K USD (750K USD total), co-PI 2020 DARPA AMP grant, 600K USD (1.8M USD total), PI 2020 SRC seed grant, 50K USD (150K USD total), PI 2020 Intel Rising Star Award, 50K USD, PI 2020 Intel Faculty Award, Performance Debugging, 75K USD, PI 2019 Google Cloud Computing Grant, 5K USD, PI 2019 Google Faculty Research Award, 80K USD, PI 2019 Intel Faculty Award, Automated Performance Optimization, 75K USD, PI 2018 Michigan College of Engineering Grant, 3K USD, PI 2018

2018

2018

2018

2017

Michigan Cambridge Research Initiative, 15K USD, PI

Microsoft Azure Cloud Computing Grant, 25K USD, PI

SRC JUMP grant, 1,25M USD (31.2M USD total), PI

Intel Gift, SysTEX'18 Workshop Sponsorship, 2K USD, PI

### **EMPLOYMENT**

University of Michigan

Assistant Professor

Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA Sep. 2017–present

Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Department

Microsoft Research

Researcher

Cambridge, United Kingdom

Aug. 2016–Aug. 2017

Research on computer systems and networks

Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL)

Lausanne, Switzerland Dec. 2015–Jul. 2016

Postdoctoral Researcher

Research on software security

• I developed infrastructure that relies on hardware support to improve software security.

Research Assistant

Sep. 2010–Dec. 2015

Research on software reliability with an emphasis on concurrent software

- I developed **Gist**, the first technique for accurately, efficiently, and automatically diagnosing the root causes of in-production failures, by using a combination of static and dynamic program analysis.
- I developed **RaceMob**, the first automated in-production data race detection technique that can be kept always-on and provides high accuracy, by combining static data race detection with adaptive, crowdsourced dynamic data race detection.
- I developed **Portend**, a high-accuracy technique to classify data races according to their potential consequences under arbitrary memory models, by using symbolic program analysis to explore multiple program paths and schedules to determine the effects of data races.
- I developed **Bias-Free Sampling**, a technique that allows efficient sampling of rarely executed code (where bugs often lurk) without over-sampling frequently executed code, by using a new sampling algorithm and existing hardware support.

Intel Corp.

Research Intern

Santa Clara, CA, USA

Jul. 2015–Sep. 2015

Automated root cause diagnosis of failures and security enhancements using hardware support

- I developed a tool that allows developers to determine which program statements operate on a given data type at runtime using a mix of static program analysis and hardware support. In our experiments, this tool reduces the number of statements to examine during debugging by an order of magnitude. This tool is being extended internally at Intel.
- I began investigating hardware support for enhancing system security, in particular, efficient path profiling for auditing and detecting control flow hijack attacks.

VMware Inc. Palo Alto, CA, USA

Research and Development Intern

Jun. 2014–Sep. 2014

Automated debugging and runtime control flow tracking

- I implemented a runtime for efficient control flow tracking in software. This work formed the basis of my **Gist** work on root cause diagnosis.
- I designed and implemented an infrastructure to remotely debug and profile VMware VCenter virtual machine management software, while it is running in production. This infrastructure is used by VCenter developers at VMWare.

Microsoft Research Redmond, WA, USA

Research Intern Jun. 2013–Sep. 2013

Efficient runtime execution sampling technique and low overhead coverage measurement

• I worked on the design of the **Bias-Free Sampling** framework for efficient runtime sampling. I designed and implemented the bias-free sampling framework for managed code (i.e., C#). This tool is internally used at Microsoft.

• I designed and implemented a fault injection tool to detect resource leakage problems using dynamic binary instrumentation.

### Siemens Corporate Technology

Istanbul, Turkey

Senior Software Engineer

Mar. 2008–May 2010

Embedded home and industrial automation software

• I designed and implemented a real-time embedded gateway software between Siemens communication processors and a building automation system using C++ on top of VxWorks.

#### Aselsan Electronic Industries

Ankara, Turkey

Software Engineer

May 2006-Mar. 2008

Embedded motor control and functional testing infrastructure

• I was responsible for a real-time embedded control software for turret motor control. I also designed and implemented a full-system functional testing software using C++ on top of VxWorks for Power PC architectures.

Student Intern Jun. 2005–Jul. 2005

Embedded software development

• I developed embedded control software for a night vision camera using C++ and PIC assembly on a PIC microcontroller.

### PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

- [1] DOLMA: Securing Speculation with the Principle of Transient Non-Observability. Kevin Loughlin, Ian Neal, Jicheng Ma, Elisa Tsai, Ofir Weisse, Satish Narayanasamy, and Baris Kasikci. *USENIX Security*, Vancouver, Canada, August 2021.
- [2] Agamotto: How Persistent is your Persistent Memory Application? Ian Neal, Ben Reeves, Ben Stoler, Andrew Quinn, Youngjin Kwon, Simon Peter, and Baris Kasikci. Symp. on Operating Sys. Design and Implementation (OSDI), Vancouver, USA, November 2020.
- [3] I-SPY: Context-Driven Conditional InstructionPrefetching with Coalescing. Tanvir Ahmed Khan, Akshitha Sriraman, Joseph Devietti, Gilles Pokam, Heiner Litz, and Baris Kasikci. IEEE/ACM Intl. Symp. on Microarchitecture (MICRO), Athens, Greece, October 2020.
- [4] Optimus: A Hypervisor for Shared-Memory FPGA Platforms. Jiacheng Ma, Gefei Zuo, Kevin Loughlin, Xiaohe Cheng, Yanqiang Liu, Abel Mulugeta Eneyew, Zhengwei Qi, and Baris Kasikci. *Intl. Conf. on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (ASPLOS)*, Lausanne, Switzerland, March 2020.
- [5] I4: Incremental Inference of Inductive Invartiants. Haojun Ma, Aman Goel, Jean-Baptiste Jeannin, Manos Kapritsos, Baris Kasikci, and Karem Sakallah. Symp. on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP), Ontario, Canada, October 2019.
- [6] NDA: Preventing Speculative Execution Attacks at Their Source. Ofir Weisee, Ian Neal, Kevin Loughlin, Thomas Wenisch, and Baris Kasikci. IEEE/ACM Intl. Symp. on Microarchitecture (MICRO), Cleaveland, USA, October 2019.

- [7] Huron: Hybrid False Sharing Detection and Repair. Tanvir Ahmed Khan, Yifan Zhao, Gilles Pokam, Barzan Mozafari, and Baris Kasikci. *Conf. on Programming Language Design and Implem.*, Phoenix, USA, June 2019.
- [8] Morpheus: A Vulnerability-Tolerant Secure Architecture Based on Ensembles of Moving Target Defenses with Churn. Mark Gallagher, Lauren Biernacki, Shibo Chen, Zelalem Birhanu Aweke, Salessawi Ferede Yitbarek, Misiker Tadesse Aga, Austin Harris, Zhixing Xu, Baris Kasikci, Valeria Bertacco, Sharad Malik, Mohit Tiwari, and Todd Austin. Intl. Conf. on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (ASPLOS), Providence, RI, March 2019.
- [9] REPT: Reverse Debugging of Failures in Deployed Software. Xinyang Ge Weidong Cui, Baris Kasikci, Ben Niu, Upamanyu Sharma, Ruoyu Wang, and Insu Yun. Symp. on Operating Sys. Design and Implementation (OSDI), Carlsbad, USA, October 2018.
- [10] Foreshadow: Extracting the Keys to the Intel SGX Kingdom with Transient Out-of-Order Execution. Jo Van Bulck, Marina Minkin, Ofir Weisse, Daniel Genkin, Baris Kasikci, Frank Piessens, Mark Silberstein, Thomas F. Wenisch, Yuval Yarom, and Raoul Strackx. USENIX Security, Baltimore, USA, August 2018.
- [11] Cntr: Lightweight OS Containers. Jorg Thalheim, Pramod Bhatotia, Pedro Fonseca, and Baris Kasikci. *USENIX ATC*, Boston, USA, July 2018.
- [12] Foreshadow-NG: Breaking the Virtual Memory Abstraction with Transient Out-of-Order Execution. Ofir Weisse, Jo Van Bulck, Marina Minkin, Daniel Genkin, Baris Kasikci, Frank Piessens, Mark Silberstein, Raoul Strackx, Thomas F. Wenisch, and Yuval Yarom. Technical report, 2018.
- [13] Lazy Diagnosis of In-Production Concurrency Bugs. Baris Kasikci, Weidong Cui, Xinyang Ge, and Ben Niu. Symp. on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP), Shanghai, China, October 2017.
- [14] Failure Sketching: A Technique for Automated Root Cause Diagnosis of In-Production Failures. Baris Kasikci, Benjamin Schubert, Cristiano Pereira, Gilles Pokam, and George Candea. *Symp. on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP)*, Monterey, CA, October 2015.
- [15] Failure Sketches: A Better Way to Debug. Baris Kasikci, Benjamin Schubert, Cristiano Pereira, Gilles Pokam, Madanlal Musuvathi, and George Candea. Workshop on Hot Topics in Operating Systems, Kartause Ittingen, Switzerland, May 2015.
- [16] Automated Classification of Data Races Under Both Strong and Weak Memory Models. Baris Kasikci, Cristian Zamfir, and George Candea. ACM Transactions on Programming Languages and Systems (TOPLAS), May 2015.
- [17] Efficient Tracing of Cold Code Via Bias-Free Sampling. Baris Kasikci, Thomas Ball, George Candea, John Erickson, and Madanlal Musuvathi. *USENIX ATC*, Philadelphia, PA, June 2014.
- [18] Lockout: Efficient Testing for Deadlock Bugs. Ali Kheradmand, Baris Kasikci, and George Candea. 5th Workshop on Determinism and Correctness in Parallel Programming (WoDet), Salt Lake City, UT, March 2014.
- [19] RaceMob: Crowdsourced Data Race Detection. Baris Kasikci, Cristian Zamfir, and George Candea. Symp. on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP), Farmington, PA, November 2013.
- [20] Automated Debugging for Arbitrarily Long Executions. Cristian Zamfir, Baris Kasikci, Johannes Kinder, Edouard Bugnion, and George Candea. Workshop on Hot Topics in Operating Systems, Santa Ana Pueblo, NM, May 2013.
- [21] CORD: A Collaborative Framework for Distributed Data Race Detection. Baris Kasikci, Cristian Zamfir, and George Candea. Workshop on Hot Topics in Dependable Systems (HotDep), Hollywood, CA, October 2012.

- [22] Data Races vs. Data Race Bugs: Telling the Difference with Portend. Baris Kasikci, Cristian Zamfir, and George Candea. *Intl. Conf. on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (ASPLOS)*, London, UK, March 2012.
- [23] Scalable Modeling of Software Product Line Variability. Baris Kasikci and Semih Bilgen. Workshop on Scalable Modeling Techniques for Software Product Lines (SCALE), San Francisco, CA, August 2009.

#### Talks Eliminating Speculative Execution Vulnerabilities • DARPA (Invited Talk) Sep 2019 **Towards Continuous In-Production Failure Diagnosis** • Ohio State University (Invited Talk) July 2018 • Greater Chicago Area Systems Research Workshop, University of Chicago (Invited Talk) May 2018 • Purdue University (Invited Talk) May 2018 Hardware-Software Co-Design for Debugging and Performance Anlysis • Workshop on Resilient Systems, TU Dresden (Keynote) Apr. 2017 Symbolic Execution: A Gentle Introduction • Cyber In Bretagne Summer School (Invited Talk) Jul. 2016 Stamping Out Concurrency Bugs • Royal Holloway, University of London, Seminar Apr. 2016 • Georgia Institute of Technology, Seminar Apr. 2016 • Carnegie Mellon University, Seminar Apr. 2016 • University of Southern California, Seminar Mar. 2016 • University of Rochester, Seminar Mar. 2016 • Microsoft Research Redmond, Seminar Mar. 2016 • Microsoft Research Cambridge, Seminar Mar. 2016 • MPI Software Systems, Seminar Mar. 2016 • University College London, Seminar Mar. 2016 • Rice University, Seminar Feb. 2016 • University of Toronto, Seminar Feb. 2016 • University of Michigan, Seminar Feb. 2016 • Boston University, Seminar Feb. 2016 • Georgia Institute of Technology, Seminar Feb. 2016 • VMWare Research, Seminar Feb. 2016 • University of British Columbia, Seminar Feb. 2016 • Simon Fraser University, Seminar Jan. 2016 Automated Root Cause Diagnosis of In-Production Failures • Symposium on Operating System Principles (SOSP) Oct. 2015 • Intel Corp. Sep. 2015 • Google Sep. 2015

• VMware Inc.

Failure Sketches: A Better Way to Debug

Sep. 2015

	I 001F
• EcoCloud Annual Event	Jun. 2015
• Hot Topics in Operating Systems (HotOS)	May 2015
Efficient Tracing of Cold Code via Bias-Free Sampling	
• USENIX Annual Technical Conference (USENIX ATC)	Jun. 2014
Lockout: Efficient Testing for Deadlock Bugs	
• Workshop on Determinism and Correctness in Parallel Programming (WoDet)	Mar. 2014
RaceMob: Crowdsourced Data Race Detection.	
• Symposium on Operating System Principles (SOSP)	Oct. 2013
• EPFL Systems Seminar	Oct. 2013
CoRD: A Collaborative Framework for Distributed Data Race Detection	
• Workshop on Hot Topics in System Dependability (HotDep)	Oct. 2012
Data Races vs. Data Race Bugs: Telling the Difference with Portend	
• International Conference on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (ASPLOS)	Mar. 2012
How to Build Reliable Software?	Mai. 2012
• Seminar talk to the incoming undergraduate students at EPFL	Sep. 2011
	•
Professional Service	
PC Chair	
EuroSys Doctoral Workshop (Euro'DW)	2021
International Conference on Virtual Execution Environments (VEE)	2020
Workshop on System Software for Trusted Execution (SysTEX) (co-located with CCS'18) Symposium on Cloud Computing (SoCC) Poster Session	2018 2018
Symposium on Cloud Computing (Society Session	2016
PC Member	
Symp. on Operating System Design and Implementation (OSDI)	2021, 2020
Symp. on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP)	2019
Intl Conf. on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (	,
EuroSys  Intl. Conf. on Virtual Europetian Engineering (VEE)	2019, 2021
Intl. Conf. on Virtual Execution Environments (VEE) Intl. Conf. on Distributed Computing Systems (ICDCS)	$2019 \\ 2019,2017$
EuroSys Roger Needham PhD Award Committee	2019,2017
EuroSys Doctoral Workshop (EuroDW)	2018
Symp. on Cloud Computing (SoCC)	2018
World Wide Web Conference (WWW)	2017
Intl. Symp. on Software Testing and Analysis (ISSTA), Artifact Evaluation Committee	2014
Journal Reviewer	
Transactions on Architecture and Code Optimization	2018
Transactions on Software Engineering	2015
Transactions on Software Engineering and Methodology	2015
Extended Review Committee	
Intl. Conf. on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (	ASPLOS) 2018
Shadow PC Member	
EuroSys Conference on Computer Systems (EuroSys)	2013, 2015

## **External Reviewer**

Symp. on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP)	2011. 2013
EuroSys Conf. on Computer Systems (EuroSys)	2011, 2012
USENIX Annual Technical Conf. (USENIX ATC)	2011
Intl. Conf. on Compiler Construction (CC)	2017
Workshop on Hot Topics in Operating Systems (HotOS)	2011, 2013
Conf. on Innovative Data Systems Research (CIDR)	2013
Intl. Conf. on Dependable Systems and Networks (DSN)	2011, 2013
Symposium on Cloud Computing (SOCC)	2012
Intl. SPIN Workshop on Model Checking of Software (SPIN)	2011

## Committee Member

EPFL Doctoral School of Computer and Communication Sciences Audit Committee

2015

## TEACHING

Introduction to Operating Systems (EECS 482) (undergrad level, University of Michigan) 2018, 2019

Advanced Operating Systems (EECS 582) (grad level, University of Michigan) 2017, 2019, 2020

# RESEARCH MENTORING

PhD	
Tanvir Ahmed Khan	Jan 2018–
Kevin Loughlin	Sep 2018–
Andrew Loveless	Sep 2018–
Jiacheng Ma	Sep 2018–
Ian Neal	Sep 2018–
Ofir Weisse	Sep 2017–May 2020
Gefei Zuo	Sep 2018–
Marina Minkin	${ m Sep} \ 2020 -$

## Master's

Nathan Brown Sep 2019–

## Undergraduate

Yineng Yan	$\mathrm{May}\ 2020-$
Dexin Zhang	May 2020–

## Alumni

Morgan Borjigin-Wang	$BSc \rightarrow Michigan MSc, 2020$
Zhiqi Chen	$BSc \rightarrow CMU MSc, 2020$
Yongwei Yuan	$BSc \rightarrow Purdue PhD, 2020$
Ruiyang Zhu	$BSc \rightarrow Michigan PhD, 2020$
Elisa Tsai	$BSc \rightarrow Michigan PhD, 2020$
Ben Reeves	$MSc \rightarrow Qumulo, 2020$
Ben Stoler	$MSc \rightarrow Johns Hopkins, 2020$
Ofir Weisse	$PhD \rightarrow Google, 2020$
Upamanyu Sharma	$BSc \rightarrow MIT PhD, 2020$
Yimeng Zhou	$BSc \rightarrow Google, 2020$
Xiaohe Cheng	$BSc \rightarrow Google, 2019$

John Wu Liran Xiao Yifan Dai Yifan Zhao  $\begin{array}{c} {\rm MSc} \rightarrow {\rm Apple,\, 2019} \\ {\rm BSc} \rightarrow {\rm UCLA\,\, MSc,\, 2019} \\ {\rm BSc} \rightarrow {\rm University\, of\, Wisconsin\, PhD,\, 2019} \\ {\rm BSc} \rightarrow {\rm UIUC\,\, PhD,\, 2019} \end{array}$ 

# LANGUAGES

English: fluent French: fluent Turkish: native German: beginner

# REFERENCES

Available upon request